<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="help.xsl"?>
<help-doc title="webCGH Help">

	<!-- ============================================================ -->
	<!--                   Overview                                   -->
	<!-- ============================================================ -->
	<section title="webCGH Overview" id="overview">
		<p>
			webCGH is a web-based application for
			plotting and visualizing microarray data, especially comparative
			genome hybridization (CGH) data.  The system allows the user
			to select microarray data sets from public as well as private
			database areas.  The user may perform preliminary filtering,
			smoothing, and normalization of data prior to plotting.  The
			system supports several types of plots:
		</p>
		
		<prop-list>
			<prop name="Scatter Plots" refid="scatterPlot">
				Plots DNA copy number measurements
				across the genome, chromosome, or chromosomal interval.
			</prop>
			
			<prop name="Annotation Plots" refid="annotationPlot">
				Shows DNA copy number measurements
				in relation to annotated genome feature, such as genes.
			</prop>
			
			<prop name="Annotation Reports" refid="annotationReport">
				Shows annotation
				genome features in a tabular format.
			</prop>
			
			<prop name="Ideogram Plot" refid="ideogramPlot">
				Shows chromosomal amplifications
				and deletions in relation to cytogenetic chromosome ideograms.
			</prop>
			
			<prop name="Probe Plot" refid="probePlot">
				Shows measured copy number for
				selected reporter probes.
			</prop>
		</prop-list>
		
		<p>
			In addition, webCGH enables the user to 
			create <ref id="virtual">virtual experiments</ref> 
			(i.e. user-defined aggregations of data) and custom 
			<ref id="pipelines">analytic pipelines</ref>, both of which are persistent.
		</p>
	</section>
	
	
	<!-- =============================================================== -->
	<!--                         Plots                                   -->
	<!-- =============================================================== -->
	<section title="Plots" id="plots">
		
		<!-- ============ Plot setup ===================== -->
		<section title="Setting up for Plotting" id="plotSetup">
		
			<!-- Selecting experiments -->
			<section title="Selecting Experiments" id="selectingExperiments">
				Clicking on the navigation bar link entitled "Data" displays
				experiments that will be plotted.  Think of this list of experiments
				as a <em>shopping cart</em>.  To add or remove experiments from the
				shopping cart click the button at the bottom of the screen.  This
				will bring the user to a screen containing checkboxes and experiments.
				Select or deselect experiments by setting and unsetting checkboxes.
				All experiments in private database areas, public database areas,
				as well as the user's <ref id="virtual">virtual experiments</ref> will be displayed.
			</section>
			
			<!-- Plotting parameters -->
			<section title="Plotting Parameters" id="plottingParameters">
			
				Plotting parameters control how data will be presented graphically
				in the plots.  All plotting parameters are set in one form and apply
				to all plots.  In other words parameters are global. Additionally,
				many of the plots are interactive.  Interacting with a plot may cause
				certain plotting plotting parameters to be set.  For instance, in scatter
				plots of the whole genome chromosome numbers are hot-linked; clicking on a
				chromosome name navigates the user to a plot of the selected chromosome.
				This has the side-effect of setting the <ref id="param-chromosome">chromosome
				parameter</ref>.  Global plotting parameters are desirable
				in that the user can easily switch between different
				graphical views of the same underlying data easily.
				
				<!-- Genome segment -->
				<section title="Genome Segment" id="param-genomeSeg">
					This set of parameters constrains the genome interval that will
					be displayed in plots.
					<prop-list>
						<prop name="chromosome" id="param-chromosome">Chromosome number</prop>
						<prop name="start" id="param-startPoint">
							Physical chromosome position of starting point of plot.
						</prop>
						<prop name="end" id="param-endPoint">
							Physical chromosome position of end point in plot.
						</prop>
					</prop-list>
				</section>
		
				<!-- Analytic Pipeline -->
				<section title="Analytic Pipeline" id="param-analyticPipeline">
					These parameters specify the analytic pipeline that will be performed
					on data before it is plotted.
					<prop-list>
						<prop name="pipeline" id="param-pipeline">
							Name of analytic pipeline.  For instructions on how to create a new
							pipeline or change settings for individual pipeline operations see
							the <ref id="pipelines">Analytic Pipelines</ref> section.
						</prop>	
					</prop-list>
				</section>

				<!-- Plot Dimensions -->
				<section title="Plot Dimensions" id="plotDimensions">
					These parameters specify the extent of the plot.
					<prop-list>
						<prop name="width" id="param-width">Width of plot on pixels.</prop>
						<prop name="height" id="param-height">Height of plot in pixels.</prop>
					</prop-list>
				</section>
		
				<!-- Plot Properties -->
				<section title="Plot Properties" id="plotProperties">
					These parameters control which features are displayed in plots.
					<prop-list>
						<prop name="Minimum copy number fold change" id="param-minY">
							This parameters has two effects:  In scatter plots it corresponds the
							minimum value on the Y-axis.  In annotation and ideogram plots is
							corresponds to the minimum saturation value for color coded
							copy number measurement.  i.e. All copy number measurements that
							are equal to or less than this value will be colored blue.
						</prop>
						<prop name="Maximum copy number fold change" id="param-maxY">
							This parameters has two effects:  In scatter plots it corresponds the
							maximum value on the Y-axis.  In annotation and ideogram plots is
							corresponds to the maximum saturation value for color coded
							copy number measurement.  i.e. All copy number measurements that
							are equal to or greater than this value will be colored red.
						</prop>
						<prop name="Fold change threshold" id="param-threshold">
							This is used in annotation and ideogram plots to filter out
							color-coded copy number data between two threshold values
							(e.g. -0.2 and 0.3).
						</prop>
						<prop name="Show annotated feature labels in plot" id="param-showLabels">
							This parameters controls if the names annotated genome features
							are displayed in annotation plots.
						</prop>
						<prop name="Show ideogram in plot" id="param-showIdeograms">
							This parameter controls if chromosome ideograms are displayed in
							plots.
						</prop>
						<prop name="Chromosome ideograms per row" id="param-ideogramsPerRow">
							This specifies the number of chromosome ideograms per row in
							ideogram plots.  Obviously it is only used when the plot consists
							of the entire genome.
						</prop>
						<prop name="Chromosome ideogram size" id="param-ideogramSize">
							This controls the relative size of chromosome ideograms in ideogram
							plots.
						</prop>
						<prop name="Annotated genomic feature types" id="param-selectedFeatureTypes">
							This control allows the user to select which types of annotated genome
							features will be displayed in the annotation plot.
						</prop>
						<prop name="Reference organism" id="param-referenceOrganism">
							This parameter has two effects: Scatter plots allow data from
							more than one organism to be plotted simultaneously.  Reference
							organism specifies which organism defines the physical probe
							positions on the X-axis.  In annotation and ideogram plots reference
							organism defines the organism from which the specified chromosome(s)
							is derived.
						</prop>
						<prop name="Specific probes" id="param-probes">
							This is used in probe plots to specify specific probes that
							will be viewed.
						</prop>
					</prop-list>
				</section>
			</section>
		</section>
		
		
		<!-- ============= Plots ======================= -->
		<section title="Plot Types" id="plotTypes">
		
			<!-- Scatter plot -->
			<section title="Scatter Plot" id="scatterPlot">
				Scatter plots display measured copy number against physical genome location.
				Users can view data at arbitrary resolutions from the entire genome on down.
				Data from multiple organisms can be plotted simultaneously.  (The
				user must select a <a href="#param-referenceOrganism">reference organism
				</a> if data from more than one organism it to be plotted.  Users may
				also display CGH and gene expression data simultaneously.  The system
				determines which data are CGH and which are gene expression data from
				user settings within the <ref id="selectingExperiments">Data Selection</ref> form.
			</section>
			
			<!-- Annotation plot -->
			<section title="Annotation Plot" id="annotationPlot">
			
			</section>
			
			<!-- Annotation report -->
			<section title="Annotation Report" id="annotationReport">
			
			</section>
			
			<!-- Ideogram plot -->
			<section title="Ideogram Plot" id="ideogramPlot">
			
			</section>
			
			<!-- Probe plot -->
			<section title="Probe Plot" id="probePlot">
			
			</section>
		
		</section>

	</section>
	
	
	<!-- ================================================================ -->
	<!--                         Virtual experiments                      -->
	<!-- ================================================================ -->
	<section title="Virtual Experiments" id="virtual">
		The system allows the user to aggregate individual bioassays from
		one or more experiments to create user-defined data sets called
		<em>virtual experiments</em>.  These groupings are stored persistently
		as cookies in the user's browser.  Note that the browser must be enabled
		to receive cookies in order to save virtual experiments.  Note also that
		virtual experiments can only be retrieved from the particular computer
		that they were created on.
	
		<!-- ============= Managing virtual experiments ============= -->
		<section title="Managing Virtual Experiments" id="managingVirtual">
			<p>
				For overall information on virtual experiments see
				<ref id="virtual">Virtual Experiments</ref>
			</p>
			<p>
				The virtual experiment management
				feature allows the user to delete existing virtual experiments
				and explore the properties of virtual experiments.  When the user
				clicks on a <em>delete</em> link the system will prompt the user
				before actually deleting the experiment to ensure that experiments
				are not inadvertently deleted.
			</p>
			
			<p>
				To access this feature click on the <em>Virtual Experiments</em> tab
				and click the <em>Manage Experiments</em> link if this page is not
				already displayed.
			</p>
		</section>
		
		
		<!-- ============= Creating new virtual experiments ========= -->
		<section title="Creating New Virtual Experiments" id="newVirtual">
			To create a new virtual experiment click on the <em>Virtual Experiment</em>
			tab and <em>New Experiment</em> sub-tab.  The system will then guide
			the user through a wizard-like process with the following steps:
			
			<prop-list>
				<prop name="Selecting Experiments" id="virtualSelectExperiments">
					The user must first select one or more experiments from which bioassays
					will be drawn for the new virtual experiment.
				</prop>
				<prop name="Selecting Bioassays" id="virtualSelectBioAssays">
					In this screen all bioassays from experiments selected in the previous
					screen are displayed.  The bioassays selected in this screen will
					constitute the set of bioassays in the virtual experiment.
				</prop>
				<prop name="Annotating Virtual Experiment" id="virtualAnnotation">
					In this screen the user must provide some basic annotation that will
					be associated with the new virtual experiment, including an experiment
					name, an organism, and a description.
				</prop>
				<prop name="Committing Virtual Experiment" id="virtualSummary">
					In this screen the user reviews information entered and commits
					the virtual experiment to persistent storage.
				</prop>
			</prop-list>
		</section>	
	</section>
	
	
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<!--                       Analytic Pipelines                          -->
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<section title="Analytic Pipelines" id="pipelines">
		When a user creates a plot webGGH may first
		invoke an <em>analytic pipeline</em> on data.  An analytic pipeline
		is a sequence of analytical operations that may filter, normalize, or
		compute aggregate statistics on data.  The system comes pre-loaded
		with default pipelines.  Additionally the user may create custom
		analytic pipelines which are persisted as cookies in their browser.  Users
		specify which pipeline is invoked through the <ref id="plotParams">
		plot parameters</ref> screen.  Here we describe how custom analytic pipelines
		are managed and created.
		
		<!-- ================= Managing analytic pipelines ================ -->
		<section title="Managing Analytic Pipelines" id="pipelines-manage">
		
		</section>
		
		<!-- ================= Creating new analytic pipelines ============ -->
		<section title="Creating New Analytic Pipelines" id="pipelines-new">
		
		</section>
	</section>
	
	
	
</help-doc>